Hello, and welcome to Lesson 29 of this introduction to calculus with Wolfram U.
The topic for this lesson is volumes of solids.
本次课程的主题是 固体体积
Let’s begin with a brief overview of today’s lesson.
让我们从本课的简要概述开始
Thus far we’ve been talking about the area under curves,
到目前为止 我们一直在讨论曲线下的面积
and we’ve used integral calculus for doing that.
并且我们已经会使用积分来计算
For example, if you work out this integral over here,
例如 如果在此计算积分
then what you’re really doing is
那么真正在做的是
to work out the area under the curve y = x^2 between 2 and 3.
计算出在 2 和 3 之间曲线 y = x^2 下的面积
The point is that you can also use integral calculus
关键是你也可以使用积分
to find the volume of solids, and that would be
计算固体的体积 那将是
a big advancement if we could learn it.
大的进步 要是我们能掌握的话
Let’s look at a very simple example of a solid like over here.
来看一个非常简单的例子 比如这个固体
What we can do is we can actually calculate
实际上我们可以算
the volume of this solid or others using calculus.
这个固体或其他固体的体积 用微积分
This lesson is about one method for computing such volumes.
这节课就是关于如何计算这些体积的
The solid that we spoke of just now was a cylinder of course,
刚才我们说的固体当然是圆柱体
and if you think of a cylinder, it can be constructed
当你想到一个圆柱体 就可以构造出来
by taking a plane region, and then you sweep out a volume.
通过先画一个平面 然后扫出一个体积
For example, let’s say you take this disk over here
例如 在这里放一个圆盘
and you sweep out a volume up to a certain height
然后扫出一个有一定高度的体积
and you get a cylinder.
你就得到了一个圆柱
That’s a hint for finding the volume of a cylinder;
这就是求圆柱体积的提示
namely, you think of it as being composed of disks.
即 当他是由圆盘组成的
If you want to find the volume of a cylinder, what you do is
如果要求圆柱的体积 就要
you take the base area
找到底面积
and then multiply it by the height to get the volume.
然后乘以高即可得到体积
For example, here’s a disk.
例如 这个圆盘
You can work out its area,
可以算出他的面积
and that’s a cylinder with that disk as a base and height 4,
那这就是以该圆为底高度为 4 的圆柱体
and its volume is 4π.
他的体积是 4π
Basically the volume of the cylinder is
基本上 圆柱的体积是
the area of the base times the height, which is 4 in this case.
底面积乘高 这里高是 4
Now of course there are many more
当然现在还有更多的
shapes and solids in the Wolfram Language
形状和固体定义在 Wolfram 语言中
and you can work out their volumes directly,
可以直接计算出他们的体积
but what you might want to do is to work out
但是你可能想算
the volumes of even more general solids.
更多的一半的固体的体积
Here’s an example.
例如
You have a three-dimensional region.
有一个三维区域
If you look at this region, you think of it
观察这个区域 就会发现
as being composed of square cross sections.
他是由正方形横截面组成的
If you were to slice the region, you would see that
对这个区域进行切片 就能看到
the area of each piece is 4x^2 because you have
每一片的面积是 4x^2 因为你的
squares with lengths and widths of 2x.
正方形长宽都是 2x
The volume of each piece would be 4x^2Δx,
每一片的体积就是 4x^2Δx
and then you can add them all up, so to speak,
所以说 把他们全加起来
and get the total volume to be the integral of 4x^2dx
就得到整个体积是 4x^2dx 的积分
between the right limits.
在确定的上下限之间
For example, if you want to define the limits as 1 and 3,
例如 如果确定上下限是 1 和 3
then the volume is 104/3.
那体积就是 104/3
Okay. Now let’s try and generalize that a bit more.
好 现在我们尝试进一步概括一下
If you have a solid with cross-section area A[x],
如果固体的 横截面 面积为 A[x]
then its volume is the integral from a to b of A(x)dx
那他的体积就是 A(x)dx 在 a 到 b 上的积分
where a and b are the limits within which you want to find the volume.
这里 a 和 b 是你想求的体积的上下限
For example, if you want to find the volume of a ball
例如 想求球的体积
like over here and the radius is r,
就像在这里 半径是 r
then each cross section has got a radius of √(r^2 – x^2).
那么每个横截面的半径为 √(r^2 – x^2)
So the cross sections of the left end have got very small areas.
因此 左端的横截面面积很小
As you go to the middle, the area increases.
当回到中间时 面积会变大
Basically, the area will be π(r^2 – x^2).
基本上 面积是 π(r^2 – x^2)
You add them all up and you get the volume of the ball,
全部加在一起就得到球的体积
which is of course (4πr^3)/3.
当然就是 (4πr^3)/3
You can check that with Volume and get back just the same result.
可以用 Volume 进行验算 并得到相同的结果
Okay. Let’s use the same idea to talk about
好 来用类似的思路来讨论
what are called solves of revolutions.
所谓旋转体的处理
Here’s a function, and what you can do is
这个函数 我们能做的是
you can take the graph of this function
可以画出函数图像
and revolve it around the x axis, and then you get a solid.
然后以 x 为轴旋转 就得到一个旋转体
Here’s how we do it.
这里怎么做呢
You use RevolutionPlot3D, and you get this solid
使用 RevolutionPlot3D 就能得到他
obtained by revolving the curve about the x axis.
通过绕 x 旋转得到
Of course you could also revolve it around the y axis
当然你也可以绕 y 轴旋转得到
and get a slightly different solid.
一个略有不同的形状
The question is how do you work out the volume in these cases?
问题是 在这些情况下如何求体积
Okay. What you do is you can again divide the volume into disks,
好 再一次我们划分体积为圆盘
but in this case, each cross section is a disk whose radius is f[x],
但是现在 每个横截面都是半径为 f[x] 圆盘
the value of the function f at x, so the volume will be
在 x 处的函数值为 f 所以体积是
the integral from a to b of πf[x]^2dx.
πf[x]^2dx 在 a 到 b 间的积分
Let’s say you want to find the volume from –1 to 1.
假设要求 -1 到 1 之间的体积
We get back the integral over here, which is 2π/5.
回到这个积分上 体积就是 2π/5
Just to remind you, that was the original parabola,
只是提醒你一下 那是原来的抛物线
and that was the solid obtained by revolving around the x axis.
这是围绕 x 轴旋转获得的固体
Now you might, let’s say, want to revolve it around the line y = 1,
现在 可能你想 绕 y = 1 旋转
in which case you just subtract off 1
这是你只需要剪去 1
because if you look at the volume over here,
因为你看这个体积公式
you see that you actually have different radii
你看实际上半径是不同的
depending upon where you are.
取决于你的位置
Basically you shift down the function by one
基本上 你把函数相加移动一个单位
to get the correct picture.
就得到了正确的图像
Then the radius of each cross section is 1 – f[x],
然后每个横截面半径为 1 – f[x]
so you can work out the volume as the integral of π(1 – f[x])^2
因此 可以将体积视为 π(1 – f[x])^2 的积分
between the correct limits.
在这个决定的范围里
Similarly, if you want to find, let’s say,
同样 比如你想求 比如
the volume obtained by revolving around the line y = –1,
围绕 y = –1 旋转所得的体积
then you add a 1.
那你加 1 就行
Here’s the picture.
这是图像
Again, work out the volume with an integral
还是 用积分算体积
and you get back the answer.
你可以得到这个答案
Basically, shift the function up by 1 in this case.
基本上 在这种情况下 将函数向上移动 1
Now a second method for computing volumes
现在计算体积的第二个方法
is the so-called washer method.
称之为 垫圈法
The idea is simple.
原理很简单
You have two functions, f and g,
有两个函数  f 和 g
and you look at the area between them
来看他们之间的区域
and then you revolve it around the x axis.
然后绕 x 轴旋转
Here’s a nice demonstration of that.
这里有一个很好的演示
You revolve it. It sweeps out the volume.
旋转他 扫出一个体积
The question is how do you work out a formula for that volume?
问题是如何得到这个体积的计算公式
What you do is you remind yourself that now each cross section
你要做的就是提醒自己 现在每个横截面
is like a washer because it’s got a kind of outer and inner radius.
像是一个垫圈 因为他有这种内径和外径
That’s the area of this washer.
底面积就是这个
We work out the integral for the volume,
我们算出这个体积的积分
and that’s the method for finding the volume using the washer method.
这就是使用垫圈法求体积的方法
But of course we might have liked to go around the y axis,
当然 我们也能绕 y 轴转
in which case we do just the opposite.
这时我们要做的恰恰相反
You write f and g as functions of y
将 f 和 g 写为 y 的函数
and then do a similar integral to get back the answer.
然后求一个类似的积分来得到答案
That brings me to the end of the lesson.
这节课就到这儿了
The main point is that you can use integrals
要点是 可以使用积分
to find the volumes of solids,
来算固体的体积
and that’s quite a powerful idea.
这是相当强大的一个思想
Let’s say if you have a cylinder, then its volume is base times height,
假设有一个圆柱体 那么他的体积就是简单乘高
where B is the area of the base.
这里 B 是底面积
If you have a more general solid with the cross-sectional area A[x],
如果更一般的固体的横截面面积是 A[x]
then you’ll compute an integral to find the volume.
那就能算个积分来求体积
If you have a solid of revolution
如果是旋转体
obtained by revolving the function around a certain line,
是函数通过绕某条确定直线旋转得到的
then you can compute its volume using the formula over here.
那你就可以用这个公式来计算
Typically you might just want y to be 0,
通常 可能设 y 是 0
so you’re revolving around the x axis.
所以就是绕 x 轴旋转
If you have two functions
如果你有两个函数
and you want to revolve the area between them,
想算他们之间区域的旋转体
then you apply the washer method and apply the formula over here.
然后使用垫圈法 在这里套用公式
Of course you can repeat the same thing
当然可以重复相同的事情
for revolving around the line x = x0.
对于绕直线 x = x0 旋转
That’s the end of this lesson about the volume of solids
本节课关于固体体积的算法就到这里了
using the so-called disk method and the washer method.
用所谓的圆盘法和垫圈法
In the next lesson, we’ll talk about another method
下节课我们讨论另一种方法
which is called the cylindrical shell method.
称之为柱壳法
That’s a little easier in some cases, but that’s for next time.
某些时候会容易一点 但是那是下节课
Do review today’s lesson.
请复习这次的课程
It’s quite a difficult lesson.
他有一点难度的
I’ll see you next time.
我们下次见
Thank you very much. I’ll stop over here.
本节课到此为止，再见
翻译：兰州大学 周怀尚